<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2914 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5405 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5405.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview SYSTEM 
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
             href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-york-rtcweb-congestion-security-xx" ipr="trust200902">
  
  <front>
    
    <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Security Concerns For RTCWEB Congestion Control</title>

    <author fullname="Dan York" initials="D." surname="York">
      <organization>Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Keene</city>
          <region>N.H.</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-802-735-1624</phone>
        <email>york@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure</area>

    <workgroup>RTCWEB</workgroup>

    <keyword>security</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>As the Real-Time Communication in WEB-browsers (RTCWEB) working group explores
      options for congestion control to ensure that browser-based voice, video and data 
      communication do not overwhelm a network, care must be taken to ensure that the
      congestion controls have appropriate security mechanisms to prevent mis-use by 
      potential attackers.</t>
      <t>This document explores potential security concerns and attacks that could be 
      made against congestion controls.</t>
      <t>NOTE: While this document is in the form of an Internet-Draft, it has been 
      created for the IAB/IRTF Congestion Control Workshop on July 28, 2012, and has
      NOT yet been submitted as an I-D.  It is written in this style, though, with the
      intent that it may be submitted as an I-D in the future.</t>
   </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Real-Time Communication in WEB-browsers (RTCWEB) working group is working
      to standardize protocols that can be used to enable interoperability between
      web browsers for interactive real-time communication using audio, video, 
      chat, collaboration, games, etc.. See <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview">draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview</xref> for an
      overview of the goals of the overall RTCWEB initiative.</t>
      
      <t>The RTCWEB working group is now exploring how best to provide "congestion control" 
      along the lines described in <xref target="RFC2914">RFC 2914</xref> and expanded 
      upon for UDP in <xref target="RFC5405">RFC 5405</xref>. The primary objectives are:
      <list style="symbols">
          <t>Prevent the collapse of a network due to congestion.</t>

          <t>Provide a level of fairness to all traffic flows on the network.</t>
        </list>
        It is expected that as RTCWEB is implemented in common web browsers the amount
        of real-time communication traffic could be quite substantial and thus the
        need for adequate congestion control is critical. </t>

        <t>Security concerns for RTCWEB have already been well-documented in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security">draft-ietf-rtcweb-security</xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch">draft-ietf-rtcweb-security-arch</xref>.
        However, the potential addition of congestion control mechanisms introduces 
        additional possible avenues of attack.</t>
        <t>While some of these attacks may be adequately mitigated by security 
        mechanisms already required for RTCWEB implementations, this document outlines 
        these potential security concerns for discussion and consideration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Potential Attacks Against Congestion Control Mechanisms">
      <t>As no congestion control mechanism is yet defined for RTCWEB, the potential
      attacks below are hypothetical and are raised as questions to be discussed.  Some
      of the proposed congestion control mechanisms may turn out not to be susceptible
      to some or all of these attacks.  Other proposed mechanisms may be vulnerable.
      This document does not make assumptions about whether the congestion control 
      mechanism might be implemented in the media stream, signaling stream or by
      some other means.</t>
       <section title="Denial of Service To An Individual User">
          <t>An attacker may want to disrupt the communication flow from a specific
          user or set of users. This could be to target a specific user or to disrupt
          a certain set of communication exchanges.	</t>
          <t>Can the attacker maliciously modify congestion control signals
          in such a way that the traffic flow from a user or set of users is significantly
          degraded to the point where communication is no longer useful?  Perhaps by
          tricking the sender into believing there is great congestion and 
          introducing excessive latency? Or signaling to a RTCWEB endpoint that it 
          repeatedly needs to switch to a different media codec? Or signaling to the 
          target endpoint that there is simply
          too much congestion for any RTCWEB communication to occur?</t>
       </section>
       <section title="Elevation of Service For An Individual User">
          <t>Conversely, an attacker might want to give higher priority to a specific
          traffic flow (including his or her own) to the detriment of other users.</t> 
          <t>Can the
          attacker maliciously modify the congestion control signals so that a particular
          traffic flow can be given higher priority? Perhaps by signaling to all other
          RTCWEB streams that there is too much congestion?</t>
       </section>
       <section title="Denial of Service For A Network">
          <t>If there is a large volume of RTCWEB traffic on a given network and a
          congestion control mechanism ensures that the traffic does not overwhelm the
          network, an attacker may find that an easy way to perform a denial of 
          service (DoS) against the entire network may be to simply remove all congestion
          control signals or convince all RTCWEB endpoints that there is no congestion.</t>
          <t>Can an attacker maliciously modify the congestion control signals to strip 
          out any such signaling? Or perhaps modify the congestion control signals in 
          such a way that sending endpoints believe there is no congestion and that they 
          can send at their highest available volumes?</t>
       </section>
       <section title="Change of Communication Mode">
          <t>RTCWEB communication is expected to allow multiple modes of communication,
          i.e. voice, video, chat, data collaboration, etc.  A RTCWEB session between two
          users might involve all of the above.  A congestion control mechanism could
          allow specification of which traffic flows receive priority and how the different 
          flows are addressed when faced with congestion.  For instance, when congestion 
          levels become too high, a video flow may be dropped while an audio or chat flow 
          may continue.</t>
          <t>Could an attacker maliciously modify congestion control signals to force such
          a downgrade?  For one or both users? </t>
       </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Inter-Domain Considerations">
    <t>A RTCWEB communication session is not expected to take place entirely within one
    network or administrative domain.  It may take place across multiple networks or even 
    more likely take place across the public Internet.</t>
    <t>Can the confidentiality and integrity of the congestion control signals be ensured
    across all the various networks through which the session travels?</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Next Steps">
    <t>The potential attacks outlined here need to be further explored to determine if 
    they are, in fact, valid attacks against potential RTCWEB congestion control
    mechanisms. Discussion needs to be held to understand if there are additional potential
    attacks beyond those listed here.</t>    
    <t>The potential attacks that are valid then need to be compared against the security 
    mechanisms defined 
    in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security">draft-ietf-rtcweb-security</xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch">draft-ietf-rtcweb-security-arch</xref> to 
    understand whether or not the attacks may be mitigated or eliminated by already-required 
    security mechanisms.</t>
    <t>Any congestion control mechanisms brought for consideration to the RTCWEB working
    group need to indicate how they address these and other security considerations.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This entire document is about security considerations.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
  
      <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2914;
      
      &RFC5405;

    </references>
  
   <references title="Informative References">
    
      &I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview;

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.alvestrand-rtcweb-congestion.xml"?>

   </references>

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2012-06-22  DY   Initial version

  -->
  </back>
</rfc>